{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The 1580s war for this country’s succession included the Battle of Ponta Delgada, a naval battle nearly 1,000 miles west of this country. In 1419, this country claimed the island of Porto Santo, part of an archipelago that is now an autonomous region with capital Funchal. Madeira and the Azores are controlled by this country, where the Douro River empties into the Atlantic near Porto. A 1755 earthquake and fire devastated, for ten points, what country’s capital city of Lisbon?",
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man worked with the ambassador Michel Ange Bernard de Mangourit during his most famous venture, which began when he arrived aboard the Embuscade in Charleston Harbor. This man attempted to hire the Anti-George and other privateers to help his country in a war against Spain and Britain, a stance opposed by George Washington. For ten points, name this Frenchman whose namesake affair tested American neutrality.",
      "answer": [
        "Edmond-Charles Genˆet",
        "Citizen Genˆet"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This government permitted the “red seal ships” to trade with Southeast Asia. This government’s Bakumatsu period, which began after the Convention of Kanagawa was signed, reversed the sakoku-era policy of isolationism. Matthew Perry negotiated with this government, which ended with the restoration of the emperor in the Meiji era. For ten points, name this final feudal shogunate of Japan which was founded in 1600 by Ieyasu.",
      "answer": "Tokugawa Shogunate"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization ran an espionage training program whose students included Ernst Wollweber and which was known as M School. A 1929 conflict pitted the forces of Zhang Xueliang against this organization. While serving as the leader of this organization, Mikhail Tukhachevsky faced an uprising of sailors in the Kronstadt Rebellion. Forces of this organization fought against neighboring Finland in the Winter War. For ten points, name this force that fought the White Army in the Russian Civil War.",
      "answer": "Workers’ and Peasants’ Red Army"
    },
    {
      "question": "Louise Stanley led this department’s Bureau of Home Economics, which produced the Aunt Sammy radio program from 1926 to 1944 and the first ever braille cookbook. Under Abraham Lincoln, Isaac Newton was the first head of what would become this department. The SNAP aid program is administered by this department, which was led by former Iowa governor Tom Vilsack in the Obama administration. For ten points, name this Cabinet department that runs the Farm Service Agency.",
      "answer": [
        "United States Department of Agriculture",
        "USDA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Thismandescribedandnamesatypeofbeautycontestwherethejudgesratebasedonhowtheythink other people will rate. This man, who proposed that it may be economically productive to pay people to bury and dig up money, famously criticized the punitive measures found in the Treaty of Versailles in his book The Economic Consequences of the Peace. For ten points, name this author of The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money, an early 20th century British economist.",
      "answer": "John Maynard Keynes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was the site of an alleged last stand at La Belle Alliance where one unit declared “the Guard dies, it does not surrender.” The Lion’s Mound monument commemorating this battle overlooks the house of La Haye Sainte. The arrival of Gebhard von Blucher’s Prussians helped decide this battle, which forced its losing commander into exile at Saint Helena. For ten points, name this 1815 battle in which Napoleon was defeated for the final time.",
      "answer": "Battle of Waterloo"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1922 in this city, a mob of boys brawled with dock workers who were wearing straw hats two days before the traditional date on which they became unfashionable. The Straw Hat Riot took place in this city, where youths living in dumbbell tenements were photographed in Jacob Riis’ How the Other Half Lives. Young men, predominantly Irish, in this city who were unable to afford a $300 fee rioted during the Civil War. For ten points, name this city where a 1935 race riot killed three people in Harlem.",
      "answer": "New York City or NYC"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once offered 500 pounds for the purchase of the twelve-year-old girl Teresa Makri, a failed bid that led to his poem “Maid of Athens, ere we part.” After meeting his cousin at a ball, he compared her to “the night of cloudless climes and starry skies” in another poem. This man, who described the travels of a disillusioned man in Childe Harold’s Pilgrimage, died in Missolonghi in 1824. “She Walks in Beauty” and Don Juan [JOO-un] were written by, for ten points, what English poet who died fighting in the Greek War of Independence?",
      "answer": "Lord George Gordon Byron"
    },
    {
      "question": "The British worked to replace this material with cordite in the 19th century. One of the earliest descriptions of this substance is in the Wujing Zongyao, an 11th century military compendium. The Mughals, Safavids, and Ottomans were known as the empires of this substance, which is made of sulfur, charcoal, and saltpeter. For ten points, name this one of the Four Great Inventions of China, an explosive material that revolutionized ranged warfare.",
      "answer": "gunpowder"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The territory that became this state was governed by the Howell Code and Hoyt Code. Jesuit Father Eusebio Francisco Kino worked with Native Americans in this state at Mission San Xavier del Bac. In 1917, the Phelps Dodge corporation deported many mine workers from this state’s town of Bisbee. In 2011, a congresswoman from this state resigned after being shot in an assassination attempt. For ten points, name this southwest state where Teddy Roosevelt supported the creation of Petrified Forest and Grand Canyon National Parks.",
        "answer": "Arizona"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This former Arizona congresswoman co-founded a gun control Super PAC after her shooting injuries forced her resignation from Congress.",
        "answer": "Gabrielle “Gabby” Giffords"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician hid his prostate cancer from the public and died in 1996 a few days after enjoying roast ortolan at his final meal. This leader controversially authorized Operation Satan, the bombing of the Rainbow Warrior ship off of New Zealand’s coast. This man was forced into a system of cohabitation with E´douard Balladur and Jacques Chirac, the latter of whom succeeded him in 1995. For ten points, name this first socialist president of France.",
        "answer": "Francois Mitterand"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rainbow Warrior was operated by this organization at the time of its sinking in 1985.",
        "answer": "Greenpeace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The musicians Stobrod and Pangle are deserters from this war in a film that focuses on the love of Ada for carpenter W.P. Inman, who enlists in it. Sergio Leone’s The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly is set against the backdrop of this war, as is Cold Mountain. Denzel Washington stars as Silas Tripp in Glory, in which he takes up his regiment’s flag at the Siege of Fort Wagner during this war. For ten points, name this war, the subject of films like Andersonville and Gettysburg.",
        "answer": "US Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Andersonville and Gettysburg were produced by this Civil War buff who founded CNN.",
        "answer": "Robert Edward “Ted” Turner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman’s daughter Alix married Theobald the Good, who had attempted to abduct this woman herself for marriage. This woman allegedly chose the gravesite of Mary Magdalene as her departing point during the Second Crusade. This woman annulled her marriage to Louis VII before marrying a king who imprisoned her for 16 years following a failed revolt that she planned with her sons John and Richard the Lionheart. For ten points, name this 12th century queen consort of England, a noblewoman from Aquitaine.",
        "answer": "Eleanor of Aquitaine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eleanor and Henry married in the cathedral of this French city, where Eleanor was probably born and where she legendarily developed a “Court of Love” to teach chivalry.",
        "answer": "Poitiers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The death of this man’s daughter Anna led him to decline one campaign for president. This man, who lived on the Ashland plantation, once dueled John Randolph. Andrew Jackson’s biggest presidential regret was supposedly that he didn’t hang John C. Calhoun and didn’t shoot this man. A tariff, national bank, and system of roads were among the improvements advocated in the “American System” by, for ten points, what Kentucky stateman known as the Great Compromiser?",
        "answer": "Henry Clay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clay’s duel with John Randolph ended peacefully, but he and a member of this family named Humphrey were each wounded in an 1809 duel. Other members of this political family included the Chief Justice in the cases McCulloch v. Maryland and Gibbons v. Ogden.",
        "answer": [
          "Marshall family",
          "Humphrey and/or John Marshall"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An artist from this country created a hyper-realistic sculpture of a pope being struck by a meteorite titled The Ninth Hour. Another artist from this country painted v-shaped rays of light emanating from a street light; that artist helped lead a movement whose manifesto declares that “a racing car is more beautiful than the Victory of Samothrace.” For ten points, name this home country of the 20th century art movement Futurism, which was led by Giacomo Balla and Filippo Marinetti.",
        "answer": "Italy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Maurizio Cattelan’s The Ninth Hour depicts this pope sprawled on the floor under a massive rock. This man was severely wounded in 1981 in St. Peter’s Square by gunman Mehmet Ali Agca [AHD-cha].",
        "answer": "John Paul II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Johann Friederich Peter’s The Psalm of Joy was performed on the first public celebration of this holiday. A hundred-foot-tall pyramid of barrels was lit as a bonfire in Salem during celebrations of this holiday. Listeners were told to “cling to this day” in an 1852 speech asking what this holiday means “to the Slave.” Both John Adams and Thomas Jefferson died on, for ten points, what national holiday commemorating the 1776 Declaration of Independence?",
        "answer": [
          "Fourth of July",
          "July Fourth",
          "Independence Day before “Independence” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This abolitionist and author of My Bondage and My Freedom asked “What, to the Slave, Is the Fourth of July?”",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick Douglass",
          "Frederick Augustus Washington Bailey"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire’s forces failed to restore Le Chieu Thong to power in Vietnam after the Tay Son Rebellion. This dynasty reformed its military with the help of Zeng Guofeng and Li Hongzhang in the Self-Strengthening Movement. The Old Summer Palace was burned during this dynasty. Hong Xiuquan, who believed himself to be Jesus’s brother, led the Taiping Rebellion against this dynasty, which aided the Boxer Rebellion against foreigners in 1900. For ten points, name this last imperial Chinese dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "Qing Dynasty",
          "Manchu Dynasty"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Empress Dowager declared war on foreign invaders during the Boxer Rebellion, but later softened her stance against foreign influence in the capital.",
        "answer": "Empress Dowager Cixi"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "1956 Bus Boycott",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Activist who refused to give up her bus seat in December 1955, sparking the boycott.",
          "answer": "Rosa Louise McCauley Parks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama city where the boycott took place.",
          "answer": "Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil rights organization that led the boycott and for which that activist worked as secretary.",
          "answer": "NAACP or National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI director who sought to discredit Martin Luther King during and after the boycott.",
          "answer": "J. Edgar Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-leader of the boycott and wife of Martin Luther King.",
          "answer": [
            "Coretta Scott King",
            "Coretta Scott"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-leader of the boycott who succeeded Martin Luther King as head of the SCLC.",
          "answer": "Ralph Abernathy"
        },
        {
          "question": "1956 court case that ended the boycott and ruled bus segregation unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "Browder v. Gayle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fifteen-year-oldactivistwhowassimilarlyarrestedbeforethebusboycott;hercasewaslesspublicized due to her pregnancy.",
          "answer": "Claudette Colvin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Crimean War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sea into which the Crimean Peninsula juts, forming the naval theater of the war.",
          "answer": "Black Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "British nurse who earned the nickname Lady with the Lamp during the war.",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major European power that allied with Britain, Sardinia, and the Ottomans in the war.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian city besieged by Lord Raglan; battles in that siege included Balaclava.",
          "answer": "Siege of Sevastopol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Force whose ill-fated charge at the Battle of Balaclava was immortalized in a Tennyson poem",
          "answer": "Charge of the Light Brigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Officer who led that charge on orders from Lord Lucan, passed incorrectly through Captain Nolan.",
          "answer": [
            "James Thomas Brudenell, 7th Earl Cardigan",
            "either",
            "both names",
            "Lord Cardigan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "November 1853 naval battle against the Ottomans that incited Britain to join the war.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sinope"
        },
        {
          "question": "Photographer whose Valley of the Shadow of Death was taken at Balaclava.",
          "answer": "Roger Fenton"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "African Civil Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the country where...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Muammar Gaddafi was killed after the fall of Tripoli.",
          "answer": "Libya"
        },
        {
          "question": "The overthrow of Siad Barre led to the Battle of Mogadishu.",
          "answer": "Somalia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jose Eduardo dos Santos led the MPLA against UNITA in a former Portuguese colony.",
          "answer": "Angola"
        },
        {
          "question": "A Marxist-Leninist state was established after the Derg overthrew Haile Selassie.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The sieges of Barentu and Massawa led to independence from the previous answer.",
          "answer": "Eritrea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince Johnson brutally murdered Samuel Doe.",
          "answer": "Liberia"
        },
        {
          "question": "RENAMO conducted a 15-year rebellion against the leftist FRELIMO.",
          "answer": "Mozambique"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ansumane Man´e led a coup against the government of Jo˜ao Bernardo Vieira in 1998.",
          "answer": "Guinea-Bissau"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Robert Wilcox tried to restore this position to power. A holder of this position established civilian wartime rights in a law that read “Let every elderly person, woman and child lie by the roadside in safety,” the Law of the (20 pts)",
        "Splintered Paddle. The Bayonet Constitution stripped power from holders of this position, whose final holder was overthrown by (10 pts)",
        "Sanford Dole. For ten points, name this royal position that was held by Liliuokalani before a US-backed coup d’etat and annexation in the Pacific."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "monarch of Hawaii",
        "King and/or Queen of Hawaii",
        "or Queen of Hawaii",
        "prompt on partial answers like “ruler of Hawaii”",
        "“queen”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before a battle in this war, a general deployed his stronger troops to the wings at the last second, leading to the “reverse” formation of an earlier battle that caused the city of Capua to change sides. This war included a siege where (20 pts)",
        "Archimedes legendarily deployed heat rays and ship-destroying claws. A general in this war lit fires far from his location in a swamp to lay an ambush in the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lake Trasimene; in response, the other side adopted the Fabian strategy. The disastrous military loss at Cannae nearly doomed Rome in, for ten points, what war against Carthage and Hannibal?"
      ],
      "answer": "Second Punic War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This political family granted asylum to Alois Brunner, a Nazi who probably died in their home country in 2010. The coup d’etat that brought this family to power shares its name with an Egyptian movement a year later; this family’s Corrective Revolution purged followers of (20 pts)",
        "Salah Jadid from the country’s Baath Party. The current head of this Alawite family is overseeing a nine year long (10 pts)",
        "civil war that broke out during the Arab Spring. For ten points, name this family whose members, including Hafez and Bashar, have controlled the Syria for nearly five decades."
      ],
      "answer": "al-Assad family"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Paw Paw Tunnel is used on one of these structures engineered by Benjamin Wright. A dispute over right of way between one of these structures and the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad was agreed to at the Point of Rocks. (20 pts)",
        "Coal from the Alleghenies was brought to Cumberland via one of these structures, the (10 pts)",
        "Chesapeake and Ohio. George Washington’s PatowmackCompanybuilt five of these structures toimprove navigationon the Potomac River. “Clinton’s Folly” was, for ten points, what type of structure that terminated at Lake Erie?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "canals",
        "Chesapeake and Ohio Canal",
        "Patowmack Canal",
        "Erie Canal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Erastus D. Culver accidentally diplomatically recognized this country’s first president Jos´e Antonio P´aez. Eulalia Ramos was a heroine of this nation, and Jose Felix Ribas helped lead the (20 pts)",
        "Admirable Campaign to free it from European control. After the Battle of Carabobo, this country gained independence as part of future Gran (10 pts)",
        "Colombia, and a Spanish attempt to recapture it failed at the Battle of Maracaibo. For ten points, name this South American country whose independence war began with the formation of the Supreme Caracas Junta."
      ],
      "answer": "Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, an investigation by Clarkson Potter found evidence of bribery in the Cipher dispatches. The highest voter turnout in American presidential history took place during this year, whose candidates included a man who had gained fame for breaking up the (20 pts)",
        "Canal Ring. The Republican candidate in this year was granted twenty (10 pts)",
        "disputed electoral votes and became president after he agreed to bring an end to Reconstruction. For ten points, name this election year in which Samuel Tilden won the popular vote but lost to Rutherford B. Hayes."
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1876"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Three Disasters of Wu were a set of attempted persecutions of this religion. During a revival of this religion in Dalit, B.R. Ambedkar began implementing mass conversion to this religion. Prince (20 pts)",
        "Shotoku developed this religion in Japan, and the Rock and Pillar Edicts are early evidence of this religion in India, where the (10 pts)",
        "Kalinga War convinced Ashoka to convert to this religion. This religion’s founder was born in modern day Nepal and gained enlightenment while sitting under the Bodhi tree. For ten points, name this Indian religion founded by Siddartha Gautama."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Buddhism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man introduced the phrase “Peace at Home, Peace in the World,” which became part of his country’s foreign policy. This developer of Sun Language Theory gave the Kastamonu Speech while wearing a Panama hat. This leader, who invited John (20 pts)",
        "Dewey to reform his nation’s education system, extended voting rights to women and forced Greeks and (10 pts)",
        "Armenians to take on new last names. This leader’s reforms included abolishing the caliphate and banning the fez. Secularism was one of the Six Arrows of, for ten points, what World War I hero who served as the first President of Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    }
  ]
}